<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of all matters passed especially in France and the Low-Countries, touching the causes of the warre now in Cleueland. Together with such occurrences of note as have happened in Spaine, Italie, England, Germany, Hungarie and Transyluania, since March last to this present, 1614. Translated according to the originall of Mercurius Gallo-Belgicus.</title>
            <author>Isselt, Michael von, d. 1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104590</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840323</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840323</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10589)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 857:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of all matters passed especially in France and the Low-Countries, touching the causes of the warre now in Cleueland. Together with such occurrences of note as have happened in Spaine, Italie, England, Germany, Hungarie and Transyluania, since March last to this present, 1614. Translated according to the originall of Mercurius Gallo-Belgicus.</title>
                  <author>Isselt, Michael von, d. 1597.</author>
                  <author>Booth, Robert, d. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by F. Kingston] for William Welby, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls church-yard, at the signe of the Swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translated by R. Boothe.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Mercurius Gallabelgicus his relation since March last, Anno 1614.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through; pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4814:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4814:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF ALL MATTERS PASSED, ESPECIALLY IN France and the Low-Countries, touching the cauſes of the warre now in <hi>Cleueland.</hi> TOGETHER WITH SVCH OCCVRRENCES OF NOTE AS HAVE happened in Spaine, Italie, England, Germany, Hungarie and Tranſyluania, ſince March laſt to this preſent, 1614. TRANSLATED ACCORDING TO THE Originall of <hi>Mercurius Gallo-Belgicus.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted for <hi>William Welby,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Swan. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4814:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4814:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIE AND HOPEFVLL GENTLEMAN, MASTER WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM BOOTHE, Eſquire: Sonne and Heire to Sir GEORGE BOOTHE, Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Jr, this Diſcourſe was brought to me in Latine by ſome of my good friends, who for that they could not pearce through the harſh and vncouth ſtile into the meaning of the Author, they prayed me to make the ſame more tranſparent by a verſion thereof into Engliſh: which J haue here done in a more explicate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and haue aduentured to recommend the ſame to your patronage, as a pledge of that affection, wherewith J doe much reſpect you. Only J beſeech you, <hi>vt facias quod iam facis,</hi> that is, that you would aduance that foundation of learning and vertue, which you haue already laid: and that you would endeuour to couple together that rare
<pb facs="tcp:4814:3"/>
ſociety of Estate and worthines, which ſo ſeldome concurre in one perſon: emulating the riches of your fortune, with the riches of your mind: by which meane you ſhall returne a noble retribution to that houſe, from which by your Match you haue receiued ſo much honour. And if you ſhall pleaſe to accept this poore Peece in good part, you ſhall bind my care hereafter to preſent you with an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both worthier for the ſtraine, and better ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with your qualitie. Jn the meane time I ſhall euer ſtudie to doe you ſeruice, and in your thoughts to deſerue the estimation</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of your very louing Kinſman <hi>ROB. BOOTHE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4814:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE FVLL OF DELIGHT, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINING THE RELATION OF THE things which in moſt parts of Europe haue paſſed <hi>worthy the remembrance, ſince March</hi> laſt. 1614. to this preſent.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>When after the lamentable ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and death of <hi>Bathorie, Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Bethline</hi> had bin appointed Prince of Tranſyluania by the Turkes, the Country was diuided into diuers fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: ſome, eſpecially theſe who were next of blood to <hi>Bathorie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to reuenge his death, of whom many periſhed about Mediſa, being throwne headlong from the tower, many followed the Emperours parts, taking Huſta, and other places in his name, but the greateſt part ſtuck to <hi>Bethline,</hi> and ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to his obedience. The Turke vnderſtanding the ſtate of the countrey, writ his letters to the Nobilitie and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Tranſyluania, to this effect; that they could not bee ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that from the time that Tranſyluania liued vnder the gouernment of his anceſtors, and himſelfe, that the country continued in great peace aed quietneſſe vnder their protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for that they had ſundry times both deſired and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aide from his Court againſt their enemies, eſpecially that <hi>Botteskay,</hi> when the Tranſyluanians were but the other day moleſted by the Germanes, being aſſiſted with his forces, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrew the power of the Germanes, and ſhaked their yoak
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4814:4"/>
from their neckes. After his death, when they ſaw that <hi>Batho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> his ſucceſſor carried things according to his pleaſure, and fell from his obedience, that <hi>Bethline</hi> with the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Nobility, complained in that behalfe of him at his Court, and that hee eaſily obtained meanes to oppreſſe him, and to free the Prouince from his tyranny. After whoſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and death, the wiſhed ſunne-ſhine of peace and liberty began to appeare, after that the clouds of troubles had by his meane been diſperſed. And now ſince the ſaid <hi>Bethline</hi> hath addreſſed himſelfe to his Court, and ſubmitted himſelfe to his order, that he hath iudged him worthy to ſucceed <hi>Bathorius,</hi> and to obtaine this Principality; and therefore that hee hath commanded, that all the Nobles of the countrie ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues vnto him, and obey his commandements, ſince by this meanes they are like to enioy their wiſhed peace and reſt. Furthermore, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame <hi>Bethline</hi> hath by letters aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed him of certaine attempts of the Germanes, and in that regard knowing aſſuredly, that this Prouince is ſetled vnder his protection, that hee had forthwith giuen order to the Commanders of Themſuard, and Agrium, and others, as alſo to the Prince of Walachia, that they ſhould haue forces in readineſſe, and ſhould bee very watchfull at all times to repell all iniuries that ſhould be offered; yea that hee did aduiſe the Nobles themſelues, that they ſhould at all times yeeld all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obedience to <hi>Bethline,</hi> ſo as they ſwarue not in the leaſt point from his commandement. And that he ſent theſe letters to this end, that they ſhould take notice of his pleaſure, and that they ſhould giue no aſſiſtance, to any attempts of the Germanes in this Prouince, whether they be ſecret or open, but withſtand them to their power, vntill the aides of The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſuard and Agrium did come, and that in all things they ſhould follow <hi>Bethline,</hi> eſteeming him as their true and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince, and continue conſtantly in his obedience, leſt they prouoke his diſpleaſure againſt them, and procure their owne great miſery. Therefore that they ſhould agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bee true to their Prince, nor ſuffer any ſtrangers to ſhuffle in amongſt them, but that they ſhould aduiſe with <hi>Bethline</hi> in all matters of importance, and entreate his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4814:4"/>
for aſſurance, taking heed that they doe not raſhly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to one ſide or other. Therefore in as much as they haue continued in obedience to him, that they ought not to doubt of his moſt mighty patronage, who meant alwaies to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that they might liue quietly and peaceably vnder the wings of his clemencie. But if they ſhould fall from their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance, and ſhal not be obedient to theſe his admonitions, that the end will be, that they ſhall bee forced to melt by his grieuous diſpleaſure, as the wax doth by the fire, and ſo bee conſumed, for that he will neuer endure that any ſhould at his pleaſure waſte and ſpoile Tranſyluania, a Prouince ſo nearely bordering vpon his kingdome.</p>
            <p>After the publication of theſe letters, hee gaue order, that certaine pikes ſhould bee ſticked in the ground, before the gates of ſundry the principall Noble men and officers cleane through Tranſyluania, in token that they ſhould die, that fell from <hi>Bethline</hi> his obedience, to the partie of the Germans, hauing placed in ambuſh certain companies, about Lippa and Geneum, which places held ſtill for the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, by whom ſome of the Garriſon ſouldiers, that ſallied out to try a fortune, were ſurpriſed, and ſlaine euery man. For which cauſe, ſome of them being ſent by their commander, came to Vienna to ſue for ſuccour.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time, a Turkiſh Embaſſador came to Lints, with letters from the great Turke to the Emperour; to this effect, that whereas he had concluded a Peace with the Emperour for twentie yeeres, that hee had for his part been very carefull that nothing ſhould be done againſt it; and that he had giuen ſtrict charge to his officers, whom hee had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the frontiers of his territories, that they ſhould giue no offence to the Emperours ſubiects, and that it was iuſt and neceſſarie that the Emperour ſhould doe the like, if he wiſhed that the Peace might continue without violation: but that now he vnderſtoode that the Emperour was raiſing forces eſpecially againſt Tranſyluania, which was a Prouince alwaies ſubiect to his Anceſtors and him, hath receiued their Princes deſigned out of his Court, and being maintained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his protection from all enemies hath liued in peace in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4814:5"/>
manner as other Prouinces haue done that be ſubiect to him. That where hee vnderſtoode that <hi>Battory</hi> did command in that Prouince with tyrannie, hee ſent an army lately to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe him, and to free his ſubiects from his crueltie: and now more, that <hi>Battory</hi> being defeated, he had deſigned <hi>Gabriel Bethline</hi> a Prince of great wiſdome and valour, to gouerne the Countrey: and haue ordered that hee ſhould vndertake the ſame with aſſurance of his helpe and aſſiſtance: but while he by all meanes endeuoured to doe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſundry waies this Peace hath been broken on the Emperours part, by the taking of the skonces of Huſta and Viuaria, and the townes of Nagipania and Toſnacum. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he deſires the Emperour, that as himſelfe is carefull by all meanes to conſerue the Peace, ſo if he be ſo affected for his part, that he would giue order to make reſtitution of the ſaid places to the Prince of Tranſyluania, or at the leaſt, that he would pleaſe by this meſſenger to let him vnderſtand his diſpoſition: who by theſe letters of his may conceiue how he ſtands affected to the keeping of the ſaid Peace. That the Peace was not at the firſt deſired by him; but the Emperour was the cauſe of making the ſame, which he doth worthily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to his owne moſt iuſt victories: that now he hath ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the Emperor what befitted his greatnes to haue done, and doth deſire y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would forbeare theſe attempts, &amp; make reſtitution of the places which he hath ſeazed vpon: for by ſo doing, the Peace is like to continue firme But if the Emperor be otherwaies diſpoſed, it ſhall hereby manifeſtly appeare to the world, whether of them hath broken promiſe, and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Peace, and that God will bring to paſſe, that which he hath decreed. To conclude, that hee deſires the Emperour that hee doe not long detaine his meſſenger with him, but with his letters giue him a ſpeedie diſpatch, leſt this long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his ſhould breede iealouſie in him, that he ſtand not ſo carefully affected to the conſeruation of the Peace.</p>
            <p>This Meſſenger being honourably intertained, was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed with expedition, with letters wrapped in cloath of golde, to this purpoſe, that the Emperour hauing with the aduice of the Electors, and Princes, and other Eſtates of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4814:5"/>
Empire reſolued touching the buſines, was ready to returne an anſwere by another Meſſenger, who was already aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on his way to the Turkes Court. Therfore that the Turke ſhould expect but a while, and in the meane time, he ſhould tempt nothing againſt the Peace.</p>
            <p>Before this time, there had paſſed diuers leagues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies, betweene the States of the Vnited Prouinces, and certaine of the Hanſe townes. Which example the towne of Magdeburge being willing to follow, had determined to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a league with them. The which the Elector of Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie miſliking, writ his letters to the Towne, that hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode from diuers places, that they determined to enter into a league with forraine ſtates, eſpecially with the ſtates of the Low-Countries: and although he conclude nothing of that buſineſſe, neither doe much buſie himſelfe to vnderſtand the reaſons which moued them to do this, yet this he took notice therof for this cauſe, becauſe he knew not whether they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into this matter with the priuitie and allowance of the Emperour, for if it were otherwiſe, they might eaſilie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue how ill the Emperour would take it. And yet, that he by no means could allow this Confederacy ſo needleſſe and euery way vnneceſſarie, but ſeeing he bare no leſſe good will to this Common-weale, then his Anceſtors had done, and would bee carefull by all meanes, to keepe and defend all harme from the ſame, that hee thought it neceſſarie with all ſpeede to diſſwade them from this league, from which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ariſe, but exceeding diſpleaſure in the minde of the Archbiſhop of Magdeburge, and many other inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences beſide. For if they had this purpoſe in contracting this league, to vndertake any hoſtilitie againſt the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and his Dioceſſe, by reaſon of the difference lately growne betweene them, that they may eaſilie thinke, that both himſelfe and other Princes and Electors, will not bee wanting to aſſiſt him, as one that is neerely linked to them in alliance. Seeing therefore he knowes very well, that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors and Princes will very ſhortly take paines to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this difference, that he hopes they will ſo carrie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that the Princes ſhall haue no cauſe to complaine of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4814:6"/>
them, and that the Archbiſhop will proue himſelfe ſuch a one as deſires not to preſſe them with any new burthen, but will condeſcend that theſe diſſentions and quarrels ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined according to lawe and equitie.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe letters ſent to the State of Magdeburge, hee wrote other letters to the ſame purpoſe vnto the Emperour, that he vnderſtood not long ſince from <hi>Chriſtianus Gulielmus</hi> Archbiſhop of Magdeburge, Primate of Germanie, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of Brandenburge, and others, that the citizens of Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburge decreed to make a league with the vnited States of the Belgicke Prouinces, and that the foreſaid Archbiſhop hath ſignified, that the ſame if it ſhould come to paſſe, would both be diſpleaſing to him, and would proue heauie and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to his Dioceſſe, and withall by their ioynt letters to the Emperour, entreated that hee would ſtop this intended league, and admoniſh the Senate and Citizens to yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and reſpect to his pleaſure. That this meſſage was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſpleaſing to him, and that they could not ſee, what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Magdeburgers had, without the Emperours know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to affect this league, and to giue occaſion to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop ſuſpiciouſly to gather matter of feare &amp; iealouſie. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therfore he holds this requeſt of the Archbiſhop very iuſt and reaſonable, and that in theſe places it is not fit to giue occaſion to draw on new dangers and troubles, but rather maturely to meet with them, eſpecially in this dangerous and hard eſtate wherein Germany ſtands, that by all meanes hee doth humbly beſeech the Emperour, that he conſidering the equity of the Archbiſhops requeſt, would interpoſe his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to dehort the Magdeburgers from their purpoſe, and gratiouſly to draw them to yeeld obedience to their Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. The Emperour hauing receiued theſe letters, diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Magdeburgers from this intended confederacy: by which meane, the Citizens alſo of Brunſwicke, who had ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them in this negotiation, returned out of the low Countries without any proceeding at all.</p>
            <p>In the moneth of Februarie was publiſhed an Edict by the Illuſtrious <hi>Iohn Sigiſmund,</hi> Marques and Elector of Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge, by way of reformation to bee executed in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4814:6"/>
of Brandenburge, directed to the Eccleſiaſticall Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the whole Electorate of Brandenburge, of both ſides the Odera, wherby they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to forbeare railing and and contentious behauiour; eſpecially in their Sermons. That godly and faithfull Magiſtrates, haue in all times and places, thought it a part of their duty, to vſe al means to ſtop vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary contentions and diſputations, who in diuers places do in their publike Sermons bitterly inueigh againſt other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as well within as without the Empire, whereof they were neuer appointed iudges, ſeeing their manner of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, are vndertaken againſt Chriſtian charity, and auaile more to hinder then to promote the edification of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, that the moſt renouned Princes &amp; Dukes of Brunſwike, and Luneburg, who liued the yeere 1562. Auguſtus, the Elector of Saxonie, who liued the yeer 1566. <hi>Chriſtianus</hi> the firſt Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Saxony, and <hi>Iohn Frederike</hi> of Ligſnits; the yeer 1601. who did the ſame in the name of the Churches of the lower Saxonie, left notable examples hereof, and worthy all imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we need not mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> higher examples of antiquity. The tranſaction paſſed with other Electors and Princes, of whom many yet doe embrace the doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi> doth perſwade and command, that a courſe ſhould bee taken, that by a godly moderation vſed in preaching, offences and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of conſciences may be auoided. Therefore that all men may eaſily iudge how diſpleaſingly hee hath taken it, and how much hee hath been affected, that hitherto of long time he hath heard, that not of all, but of many in his Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and indeed ſuch, who being moued with ambition rather then zeale of Piety, are likely perſons either to do leaſt, if they were brought to a iuſt triall in argument, or to fall to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh partie, if they could make but ſix pence more, ſhould fill al Churches &amp; Pulpits with their imprecations, criminations, calumnies, curſings and ſuch like outcries, ſeeking rather glory with men then with God: little regarding whether they ſpeake true or falſe: and whether it were conuenient or inconuenient to ſo holy a place, ſo as they might gall, and bite other Chriſtians, ſatisfie their humors, ſpend their cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and moue laughter to our common enemies, the Ieſuites,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4814:7"/>
and other Papiſts, and giue them occaſion to ſlander vs, by this meanes heaping vp the diſpleaſure of God againſt them and their Auditorie in the day of iudgement. That the holy Scripture doth teach vs farre otherwiſe: for it doth not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that they who agree with vs in the ground of Religion, and ſtedfaſtly reſolue to be ſaued by the only grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, for and thorow the merit of our onely Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, all other meanes quite excluded, who alſo labour with vs in the vineyard of Chriſt, and therefore doe ſuffer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable perſecutions from the common enemies of true Religion, the Pope and his Miniſters; nay more, who with great cheerfulneſſe and plentie doe euen ſpend their blood for this Confeſſion, ſhould be excluded out of the Church of Chriſt. Neither would the holy Scripture, that that which is doubtfull, ſhould bee argued by accuſations and ſlanders, which is proper to Satan, or by coniectures and falſe allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but by the infallible word of God. Therefore that hee doth ordaine and ſeuerely charge, that all Paſtors and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Churches, doe in the Churches purely and ſincerely teach and propound to their Auditors the word of God, out of the Prophelike &amp; Apoſtolike writings, the foure Symbols receiued in the Church: the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> confeſſion reformed, and the Apologie thereof, without all deprauation, and omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all interpretations, and phraſes, and new formes brought in by idle and ambitious Diuines, that they endeauour to gaine ſoules to Chriſt, and direct all their labours to aduance the glory of God, and the ſaluation of men: and on the other ſide, that they wholly abſtaine from criminations, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of other Churches, which neither are ſubiect to them, nor conuicted of errour by any lawfull and ordinarie courſe: not branding them with any name of Hereticke, for that he being vrged in his conſcience can no longer winke at theſe things, but hath determined when hee ſhall know that any, whoſoeuer hee be, doth offend againſt this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, (which cannot bee hid from him long,) that firſt hee will ſummon him to appeare at his Court, there firſt by ſpeech to check his folly, and if he can doe good with admonitions, either to remoue him from his place, or chaſtiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4814:7"/>
him with ſome puniſhment: and courſes beſides ſhall bee taken for obſtinate fellowes, who vpon ſummons doe not appeare at our Court, whereby they may eaſily bee brought to obedience. But if there be any who being carried with an intemperate zeale, ſuppoſe by this meanes that a curbe is laide vpon their conſciences, that hee will not bee againſt it, but that they may giue ouer their Miniſtery, and with leaue depart out of his Electoratſhip, and go to thoſe places where they may bee ſuffered to rage; and to wound Chriſtians, to curſe and execrate, expecting at the laſt from God a iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of their intemperate fury.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that he doubts not, but that as this Edict hath been publiſhed by him, by the preſcript of the word of God, to keepe the Peace, tranquilitie and concord in the Churches of thoſe countries, which by God are committed to him, in theſe laſt and dangerous times, wherein the Antichriſt of Rome ſeemeth more then euer before to thirſt after Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an blood, all and euery one, in regarde of the commandement of God, whereby ſubiects are by the Apoſtle commanded to bee obedient to their Magiſtrates, that they will conforme themſelues to obedience, and take care not to prouoke his diſpleaſure againſt them, leſt they bee forced to trie to their loſſe and griefe, that they beare not the ſword in vaine: the heads of the Articles, according to which this reformation was to be practiſed in the Churches, were ſaid to be theſe.</p>
            <p>That images ſhould be baniſhed out of the Churches: the Altars that were made in time of Poperie, to be demoliſhed, and long tables of wood to bee ſet in their places, couered with a blacke carpet, and a white cloath vpon it, when the Supper is to bee adminiſtred: That the ſtatues, images and croſſes, drawing their beginning from Poperie, are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued out of the Churches. That their holy Palles are no more to be vſed. Candles not to be lighted. Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to be laide aſide. Prayers in the Pulpit to bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not ſubmiſſely, but with a loud voyce. That in time of danger, eſpecially in the time of Plague, the Supper of the Lord is not to be giuen to the ſicke. The Decalogue and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme to be better reformed. That the bleſſed Trinitie is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4814:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to be repreſented by no images, either grauen or painted; the words of the holy Supper to be vnderſtoode and expounded, in the true and right ſenſe: with ſome other Articles as it was reported.</p>
            <p>Some yeeres paſt, and before the Peace made with the confederate States of Holland, a Seafaring man of Holland, had been taken by the Maſters of the Spaniſh Inquiſition, and had been condemned to the fire for a Pſalme booke one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which was found in his cuſtodie, but by ſome ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice hee eſcaped that danger; but afterward returning into the ſame place againe, as being ſecure from feare, by reaſon of the League, hee was againe taken by the Inquiſitors: and notwithſtanding the interceſſion of the States to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke, who writ to the King in the priſoners behalfe, hee was condemned and burnt aliue.</p>
            <p>His kinsfolkes haue made many complaints to the States for this crueltie, and to reuenge the ſame, haue intreated ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, that they may haue leaue to ſaile into the Weſt Indies.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of Aprill was an honourable mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Electors and Princes at Naumburge in Thuring, the Elector of Saxony with his brother <hi>Augustus,</hi> the Elector Brandenburge, and many other Princes, to conclude and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of the hereditarie league betweene the noble families of Saxony, Brandenburge, and Haſſia, of the precedencie of the houſes of Vinaria and Alkenburge, and of the doubtfull and controuerſed buſines touching Gulicke and Iuliers.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, ielouſies and vnkindnes euery day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing betweene the Princes of Brandenburge and New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge, many of the Electors and Princes laboured to bring them to accorde. But the States of Cleueland aſſembling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, agreed to incline to neither ſide of the foreſaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor to allow any contribution to them, vntill they were aſſured of their true ſucceſſor and Maſter, and at once ſending their letters to the Archduke <hi>Albert,</hi> to the Elector of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, &amp; to the Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces of Belgium, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted them that they would haue no hand in this buſines, but that they would leaue it to be determined betweene the Princes themſelues: to whom the Elector of Collen anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4814:8"/>
that for the great deſire he had of peace, hee would be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnwilling that any warre ſhould ariſe, eſpecially in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and Countries neighbouring vpon him; and yet if the Prince of Newburge ſhould haue any wrong done him in his right pretence, that by no meanes he might forſake him, and ſending to Duſſeldorpe <hi>Reckius</hi> his Embaſſadour, exhorted the Princes who were ſeaſed of ſome places, to leſſen their traine. And although they fell to the number of twentie fiue attendants, yet the Brandenburgian preſently changing his purpoſe, after that the Newburgians, laying aſide their armes which they carried cloſely; that is, Piſtols, and other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, which might bee tied vnder their cloakes; and walking onely with their ſwords by their ſides, anſwered, that he alſo would willingly condeſcend to all reaſon and equity, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the determining of the queſtion of ſucceſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them: and forthwith departing to Gocha, within the Principality of Cleue, hee ſent his Embaſſadours to the Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces, who by all meanes exhorted both the Princes to auoide trouble, and to conſerue peace.</p>
            <p>But when the Eſtates vnderſtood that the King of Spaine had commanded his ſouldiers to be in a readineſſe, they alſo gaue order to haue Waggons prouided, that if neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired they might carrie their ſouldiers thither, where the Spaniſh forces ſhould bend. Which prouiſion gaue the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke occaſion to write to them, to this effect. That he lately was aduertiſed by the Eſtates and Councellors of the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Cleue, of differences growing betweene the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Princes, <hi>George William</hi> of Brandenburge, and <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangus William</hi> of Newburge, and of the dangers which ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hang ouer the whole Countrey, with a requeſt alſo from them, that to his power he would for the conſeruation of the common peace, meet with theſe difficulties. Therefore that he being moued with the requeſt of them of Cleue, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that it imported him very much, that his neighbours ſhould liue in peace, had by his letters aduiſed the Princes, that as louers of peace they would entertaine loue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and with all diligence auoide troubles, adding withall a proteſtation, that hee in regard of the peace and right hee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4814:9"/>
hath to maintaine ouer thoſe places, that he of neceſſity muſt bee an enemy to him, who is the firſt author to moue any ſtirre. And although hee doubt not but that they are of the ſame mind with him, and will not ſuffer that any dore ſhould bee open to ſo great dangers and troubles, yet that hee was willing to deſire them, that if they thought good, themſelues would beſtow ſome paines to conſerue the publike peace, which wil very ſoone be violated and diſturbed in theſe parts, if theſe Princes ſhould fall together by the eares.</p>
            <p>There was offered to the Emperour about the beginning of Aprill, the declaration of <hi>Wolfangus William</hi> Prince of Newburge, his ſubmiſſion in the Mulheme buſineſſe. But the Elector of Brandenburge would in no ſort ſubmit the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be deſided by the Emperours Councell of Court, but endeuoured by all meanes that it might bee remitted to the Imperiall Chamber; in which behalfe he wrote to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to this effect. In that he had not to this time returned an anſwere to the Emperours letters, touching a new hearing of the buſines of Iuliers, that he did it not of purpoſe, nor of any intent to delay the matter, but for waighty conſiderations which hindred him. But that indeed there are many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which hinder that hee may not condeſcend to yeeld to this treatie of the buſineſſe: for that it is euident by the relation of the Count Hoelſoller, ſent from Erford to the Emperour the laſt yeere, how deceitfully he was dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, who hauing nothing but hony vpon their tongue, did by all meanes ſtudie to beſmeare his face. And ſince this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by the foreſaid Earle, who profeſſeth himſelfe a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his houſe, and is by oth obliged to him, for his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarie Office of the Chamber, which hee holds of him, that he may eaſily imagine how farre hee is to truſt others in this cauſe, who are not in that place of relation to him. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that his feare and iealouſie is not a little encreaſed by that ſame dangerous and moſt pernicious decree in the buſineſſe of Mulheme, which a few daies ago <hi>Iohn Ludouike</hi> of Vlmes, bearing the Chancellors perſon in the Emperours Court, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to bee intimated to him, although in the whole yeere nothing was done to his knowledge in that cauſe in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4814:9"/>
Court, not ſo much as by way of ordinary talke. Whereby it may eaſily appeare what affection the Emperours officers car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie towards him. Although therefore he hath good reaſon to looke to himſelfe, being admoniſhed by theſe former ſteps, nor to commit any thing that may concerne him to ſuch kind of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwithſtanding paſſing by all theſe things, to ſhew his care to yeeld to the Emperour his due reſpect, that hee ſubmits his cauſe to this treaty, with this condition, if firſt he may vnderſtand, whether and how theſe other competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors doe ſubmit themſelues. Secondly, if it proceed not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then is fit to proceed in a friendly hearing, and that hee may be at no preiudice, if they cannot agree, or any decree be made that is hurtfull to him: but that all things bee left in the ſame ſtate they were before the treatie, vntill this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be determined in a lawfull manner. Furthermore, ſince he hath taken the poſſeſſion of the Principality of Iuliers in a manner lawfull, and by all law to bee allowed, (conſidering what the Archduke <hi>Leopald,</hi> and the Biſhop of Paſſauium haue done) and that the Emperour himſelfe hath paſſed his promiſe, which he hath reaſon to beleeue, to maintaine euery one in his poſſeſſion, nor to remoue him from it, but by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deciſion of the buſineſſe going before, that it is a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thing to trouble the treaty with the point of the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is onely to be directed to the point of chalenge for the right: otherwiſe if they doe, that hee will admit no treaty at all, ſeeing alſo vnleſſe he be admitted in the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Fee: yet without preiudice to others, hee may eaſily perceiue that for the point of the challenge hee ſhould bee neglected, that hee doth beſeech the Emperour that hee would alſo conferre vpon him this Fee, as hath been done to others, and ſo make him equall to the reſt; and that he hopes, that the Emperour will chuſe into this buſineſſe Arbitrators honeſt and ſwayed with no preiudice, nor enclining to either ſide, but indifferent and equally affected to them both. Laſtly, ſince he is not ignorant, that certain haue gone about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the late Emperour, that he hath ſome intereſt as Lord Paramount ouer theſe countries, &amp; that this <hi>dirictum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> ſo called, and the prerogatiue of the Emperour annexed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4814:10"/>
to it, may not bee called into queſtion: that he deſires of the Emperour, that hee may vnderſtand what hee may expect from him in this point, and that with conuenient ſpeed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he hath receiued anſwere to all theſe things, and that the certaine time, when this hearing ſhall begin, bee ſet downe by the Emperour, that hee will take care that no want bee found in him. Other matters hee would haue referred to this future hearing, but that hee beſeecheth the Emperour not to bee offended with him, but that he would preſerue his right to him, no leſſe then to others. That he could haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued this anſwere, and his exception to the time that this Treatie begins, but to ſaue time and expence, and that the Emperour may ſee the ſinceritie of his mind, which he brings to the handling of this buſines: that hee was willing afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand to open his mind to the Emperour, before any entrance into the matter, to whom hee profeſſeth himſelfe moſt ready to doe all ſeruice.</p>
            <p>About the end of Aprill was taken a Pirats ſhip, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in her aboue 60. braſſe peeces, and was very rich beſide, which lay in waite vpon the coaſt of Ireland, for foure Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſhippes, which a little after came out of Ginnie very richly laden with gold and ſpice: ſhee was carried to Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</p>
            <p>There came at the ſame time into Holland, Embaſſadours from Muſcouia, whom the Eſtates cauſed to be brought with a great traine from Leiden to the Hage, the 11. of May, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted into the Councell houſe, they declared in a long ſpeech, that their great Duke, did by all meanes deſire the friendſhip of the Eſtates, and deſired them that they would furniſh him with money and ſhipping againſt his enemies: being there willed to exhibit in writing this their requeſt, they did ſo. But when it did not appeare, what profit might returne to the States out of Muſcouie, they fearing leſt they might offend the King of Poland, after deliberation, made them this anſwere conceiued in writing, whereby they might aſſure the great Duke of Muſco of their friendly minds, and great good will towards him, and ſo diſmiſſed them with roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all intertainement, and great gifts. Count <hi>Maurice</hi> preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4814:10"/>
to them a gallant ſhew of a battell, according to the true manner of Military diſcipline, which they beheld with great admiration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suigelius</hi> the Maſter of the horſe, hauing aſſaied Duſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorpe, Cleue, and other places, when all his ſecret practiſes would not preuaile, at the laſt was receiued into Gulick by the Gouernour <hi>Pythamius,</hi> with whom hee had ſecretly plotted the ſame before, bringing into the towne diuers companies of the Eſtates ſouldiers. For when <hi>Pythamius</hi> did ſee that the Caſtle of Gulicke was in great danger, by reaſon of the vnkindneſſes, which euery day grew more and more among the poſſeding Princes and their friends, the Brandenburgian and Newburgian garriſons, being ready to fall to blowes, he thought it the fitteſt way to draw in theſe companies of the Eſtates. The Captaines of the garriſon ſouldiers, as wel Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgians as Newburgians, being ignorant of any pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, forth with tooke armes: but being perſwaded by the ſaid Gouernor, and <hi>Suigelius, Hancrote, Bonnus,</hi> and other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of thoſe forces, that it was for the good of both the Princes, the Bandenburgians were pacified: but the Newbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians giuing no credit to them, made ſharpe reſiſtance, till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome blowes, and ſlaughter of diuers, they came to agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and were contented. Which done, <hi>Hancrote</hi> and <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> hauing commiſſion for that buſineſſe from <hi>Graue Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> continued in the Caſtle with their forces, and haue ſince ſtrengthened the fame with 7. companies of horſe and foote, drawne out of the Vnited Prouinces, making beſides great prouiſion of victuall and other neceſſaries to keepe the place.</p>
            <p>Which when the Prince of Newburge vnderſtood, he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted certaine Officers and Councellers of the Prince of Brandenburg, remaining at that time at Duſſeldorpe: and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patching Meſſengers to diuers places, exhorted the Officers of Cities and Gouernours of Caſtles, that, as mindfull of the oath they had taken, they would keep diligent watch in their townes, and vſe all circumſpection againſt ſuch manner of traines and practiſes. But for the defence of the Citie, hee thought good to let in the ſouldiers; which when the Burgers did earneſtly withſtand, he inuited all the chiefe Senators to a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4814:11"/>
banquet, in which time certaine Muſqueteirs, ſlipping out at the Poſterne gate, made themſelues maſters of the towne watch, and let in the Country ſouldiers, who the next day were beſtowed at the Gates, their number increaſing euery day, and bulwarkes and forts raiſed againſt the gates. In the meane time, the ſouldiers of the Eſtates aſſaulted the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Scheiuenhem, and they of Brandenburge the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Siburge, but both in vaine. But when the Archduke heard of the newes of the ſurpriſing of the Caſtle of Gulicke: forthwith hee muſtered his ſouldiers, and made preparation for this iournie; the Vnited Eſtates alſo doing the like, which bred ſuch a feare among the Countrie people of Iuliers, that they took al their goods, and carried them to Vtright, Leids, Collen and other places.</p>
            <p>There was mention made in our former bookes of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Aken, and for them wee are now come to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the proſcription. Therefore the Elector of Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge writing his letters to the King of France, deſired him that he would in time interpoſe his authoritie: who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay diſpatched his letters to the Elector of Collen, to dehort him from the execution of the ſentence: that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Emperor againſt the city of Aken, to ſtrike it with the thunderbolt of Proſcription, for thoſe things which there fell out in the time of the vacancy, in the name of his kinſman the Palatine Adminiſtrator, and vnder the title of his Vicariat in the Empire, was very diſpleaſing to him; therefore waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger, which by the execution of this ſentence ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to threaten the Peace of Germany, which it concerneth neerely, that this citie ſhould be preſerued, that hee as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince, whoſe part it is, by all meanes to maintaine the publike Peace among the Confederate Princes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that hee could not forbeare to put him in mind of the miſchieuous and dangerous iſſue; which peraduenture this execution may haue, therefore that he deſires, that he would pleaſe to take notice from <hi>Praeauſtie</hi> his Embaſſadour, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Flanders, of thoſe things, which he hath giuen him in charge, eſpecially on the behalfe of his kinſman the Palatine Elector.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4814:11"/>Theſe letters were ſent to the Kings Embaſſadour <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier de Preux,</hi> with other letters beſides to him to this purpoſe. That he hath ſent to him the copies of thoſe letters, which he had receiued from the Elector Palatine, in the matter of the Aken-buſines, which paſſed during the vacancie, and when the Vicariate of the Empire fell to him, that by them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what he challengeth to belong to him, touching the execution of the Proſcription decreed againſt this citie, and committed to the Archduke <hi>Albert,</hi> and Elector of Collen, and of the right, which the Palatine Elector in this cauſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to belong to him, hee may obſerue and diſcerne how much the Palatine doth promiſe to himſelfe for the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the peace in Germany by the interſeding of his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with theſe Commiſſioners. Seeing therefore there han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth no ſmall danger ouer whole Germany by this execution, eſpecially if the Princes ioyning together, ſhall earneſtly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues againſt it, that he hath ſent him letters, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Elector of Collen, &amp; chargeth him to deliuer them to him, and that he would propound to his conſideration the waight of the whole buſineſſe, as alſo the declaration of the right which he hath, in hindring this endeuour of his againſt the Palatine Elector, and the dangerous accidents tending to the miſchiefe not onely of the citie of Aken, but alſo of the whole Empire, together with the demimution of the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and honour of the Emperour: and that hee write backe withall ſpeed to aduertiſe him how farre hee hath preuailed with him.</p>
            <p>In the former bookes, we ſpake of the broiles which were raiſed in France, with a commemoration of the grieuances exhibited to the Queene by certaine principall perſonages, and the anſwere to the ſame. And ſeeing it concerned the Common-wealth very much, that the ſeedes of troubles ſhould bee choaked in the very bud, and the ſparkles of fire quenched in the very kindling, before they bee able to take flame, <hi>Lewes</hi> the moſt Chriſtian King, when he vnderſtood that a meeting was appointed by the Princes at Soiſſons, the 7. of April, incontinently ſent certaine of his Councellors thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ſhould giue remedy to their grieuances, and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compoſe all differences, furniſhed with letters of credence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4814:12"/>
to this effect; that as before he had ſent them to Soiſſon, that they might treat with the Prince of Condie, and others there aſſembled, ſo at this time eſpecially He, the Queene Mother, and the reſt of the Counſellors and Princes conſenting, doth will, and giue them full power, that looke what conditions they ſhall thinke honeſt and indifferent, for the mature com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of their troubles, they ſhould accept, and aſſure in his name, that they ſhall be faithfully obſerued in Court, and that they do all things, which hee himſelfe would doe, if hee were there preſent. And if ſo be that this Treatie ſhall require any more ſpeciall commiſſion, that hee doth promiſe in the faith and word of a King, that whatſoeuer ſhall in this buſineſſe be done, tranſacted, concluded, decreed, and promiſed, that hee will hold it, <hi>ratum &amp; gratum:</hi> that is, it ſhould bee as ſtrong, and as well pleaſing to him, as if he had done it himſelfe, and that he will by ſpeciall edicts giue commandement, that it be executed, and this power ſhall euery one haue, although they ſhall be hindred either through ſickneſſe, or any buſines, that they could not bee there. This Treatie failed not of his wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed profit: for they agreed vpon certaine articles of Peace, which were afterward ratified at San-Manehold, to wit, that vpon the ſummons of a generall Parliament, all the States of the kingdome ſhould aſſemble at Sene, the 25. of Auguſt: and there it ſhould bee lawfull for the deputies of the three Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to propound thoſe things, which in their conſcience they ſhall find to be profitable for the good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, and eaſe of the ſubiects, that ſo the King vpon aduice with his kinsfolke and other Princes, may in conuenient ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, publiſh wholſome conſtitutions, renue ancient decrees, and annull and abrogate Orders made to the deſtruction of the ſubiect. That the marriages vndertaken with the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, ſhould remaine in their full force, ſeeing the Queene Mother hath by her letters, giuen ſufficient reaſon for them to the Prince of Condie, that the bulwarkes of the Caſtle of Meſſeron, ſhould be throwne downe, and that the requeſt of the Duke of Niuerne ſhould bee ſatisfied, touching a certaine ſumme of money, which hee demands of the King, for buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a houſe in liew of that, which he had at Maſſera, which was throwne downe, when the caſtle was builded.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4814:12"/>
That the Caſtle of Blauet, which in the time of theſe troubles was ſeaſed, and began to bee fortified, ſhould bee razed to the ground, and the place to be left in the ſame ſtate as it was before the troubles, the Captaine and guard remoued out of it; which Order muſt be conceiued generally to extend to the reſt of the caſtles and forts, which were euery where raiſed in the Prouince, during the troubles. That for auoyding and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the charges and inconueniences, which the ſubiects endured by the ſouldiers, as well French as ſtrangers, which were hitherto leuied, &amp; diuerfly ſcattered in the kingdome, in the name of the King and Prince of Condie, from the Kalends of Ianuary, al ſouldiers on both ſides ſhould be diſmiſſed, and the ſtrangers ſhould within twelue dayes from the ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Articles bee conueyed out of the kingdome by Commiſſioners deputed by the King and Prince, and the French ſouldiers ſhould within the ſaid time, withdraw themſelues to their owne houſes, vnder the paine appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for vagabonds and rogues. That the Prince of Condie by the Kings permiſſion, ſhall keepe the towne and caſtle of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyſe, with 100. garriſon ſouldiers for his ſecuritie, vntill the time of the general Parliament. That the Duke of Vendoſme, if he returne to his houſe, and reſt contented with theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſhould be reſtored to his place, and enioy his former ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as before, all manner of inhibitions being taken away and aboliſhed by the publike Edicts, that they may preiudice nor hurt him any more. That hee receiued money of the chiefe of the Prouince to maintaine his armie, the King ſhould allow. Likewiſe for one whole yeere complete, the King ſhould maintaine the forces appointed for Machen, and Bell Iſle, if the Captaine of Retſe ſhall require the ſame. That the damage, which was done to <hi>Monſieur de Camore</hi> at Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebon, where he is Commander, ſhould be recompenſed, and he reſtored to his former office and dignitie. That all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſouldiers brought into the cities and townes of this Kingdome, during this commotion from the Kalends of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie vntill this time, ſhould be diſſolued, except 100. ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers at Maſſire, and 200. at Soiſſon, vnder the command of the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> which are to continue vntill the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4814:13"/>
be finiſhed, ſeeing that other Cities and Townes ſhould be reſtored to their former eſtate. That the King by his letters ſent to all the Parliament, ſhould ſignifie and make knowne that he is ſufficiently perſwaded, that the Prince of Condee and other officers of the kingdome, of what eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoeuer, who followed them in this commotion, attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing of any euill purpoſe, neither did fall from their obedience due to the King, adding a neceſſary both excuſe, and aſſurance, that they need not be called into queſtion for them, but that they ſhould bee againe reſtored to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Dignities and Offices, and enioy the profits of them as before: And that letters ſhould be diſpatched to the confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes and Eſtates, and that they ſhould truly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with all ſpeed by certaine fit Meſſengers for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, what the King doth aſſuredly know touching the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and loyall affection of the Prince of Condee and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther officers. That the King ſhall pay to the Prince of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee for the charges of him and other officers during theſe troubles, the ſumme of foure hundred and fiftie thouſand pounds to bee diuided by him among the Princes and other Officers. Theſe matters thus being ordered, and allowed and confirmed by the King, the Prince of Condee, and other Princes and Officers of the kingdome diſclaimed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced all confederacies vndertaken either within the kingdome, or without, and promiſed neuer to enter into any league any more. On the other ſide, the King granted to the Duke of Niuerne his letters Patents, to him and his eldeſt ſonne of the gouernment of Champaine.</p>
            <p>Theſe buſineſſes in this manner being paſſed, and all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement ſigned and ſealed by the King himſelfe, the Queene Mother being Preſident, and alſo by the Prince of Condee, and <hi>Ventadurius,</hi> the Duke of Bullion, and other Princes, the Prince of Condie wrote his letters to the Queene Mother, wherein he profeſſed that both in regard of her great good will before time declared vnto him, and alſo for the great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour ſhee had done him in this preſent treaty, that hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged himſelfe ſo much obliged to her, that hee could not forbeare to giue her great thankes for this royall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4814:13"/>
of hers towards him: but hee did beſeech her that ſhee would waigh courteouſly and equally with her ſelfe by what freenes of mind hee was impelled to vndertake theſe buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who if he might haue liued without the malice of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries that lay in waite to ſurpriſe his honour and eſtate, had neuer proceeded ſo far, neither had any ſtir beene made in the kingdome. But now all matters being ſtilled and quieted by the grace of God, and the wiſdome of the Queene, that he did earneſtly beſeech her that ſhee would ſo order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne all things hereafter, that no occaſion may bee offered to the renewing of the like Commotions; for that hee for his part would alwaies be moſt ready in his place to performe all manner of ſeruice to the King his maſter.</p>
            <p>While theſe things paſſed in France, there appeared at Prage, and thorow all Bohemia a Sunne Circle called Paralia, and two Sunnes ſeemed to appeare in heauen. At Nemeth in Hungarie, a fountaine neare to the walles of the City brake forth with great force into ſtreames of blood, almoſt by the ſpace of an houre. At Butoarium a woman brought forth a monſter, reſembling a Seafiſh. And another woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a village not aboue a mile from Prage, brought forth a child with one body, but fearefully ſhaped, with foure hands, and foure feet, which liued vntill the next day. A little before in Carinthia it rained a kind of red graine, whereof there was baked good bread, which was brought ouer by certaine Merchants from Villacum. And euen at this time was ſeene in the aire a red Croſſe, not without great wonder and terrour to the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>Almoſt about the ſame time, being the fifteenth of May, <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangus William</hi> neglecting the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> Confeſſion, fell to the Pope, and embraced the Romane Religion, and at a Maſſe, which was celebrated in the pariſh Church of Duſſeldorpe, with great ſolemnity and all manner of muſicke, hee with his wife receiued the Sacrament after the Popiſh manner. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Sermon was made by the Deane of the Church, out of the third Chapter of <hi>Iohn,</hi> wherein alſo the reaſons were deliuered, for which the Prince had withdrawne himſelfe into the boſome of the Romane-Catholicke Church. After
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4814:14"/>
a few daies a Nuncio came from the Pope, accompanied with certaine Capuchine Monkes, to Duſſeldorpe, to conferre ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie abſolution and benediction vpon the Prince, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him to conſtancy.</p>
            <p>This reuolt and change of <hi>Wolfangus</hi> bred great ſorrow and griefe in the mind of <hi>Philip Ludouicke</hi> Prince of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge the father, and ſince that which was done could not be vndone, being ſollicitors in the behalfe of his ſubiects, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to fall to prayer for the conſeruing of the ſincere and wholeſome doctrine of the Goſpell, and to that end pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed an Edict to be obſerued by all the Paſtors of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to this effect. For as much as he hath ordained and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the Paſtors and Miniſters which is in the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality of Newburge, that they carefully prouiding againſt this preſent neceſſity, and the eminent fearefull change of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that not only they themſelues doe meete in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches euery Monday at twelue of the clocke, to powre forth prayers to God with their hearers, but alſo that they be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that the ſame be done by the Miniſters and Preachers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Iuriſdiction, that he doth ſtraightly command and enioyne them all that they giue good example to their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and that they the time and place aforeſaid, and together with their Auditors, men, women, and children, and their whole families, they doe beſeech the Lord to turne away the danger, which now is at hand, and that in the ſolemnizing of publike prayers, they doe premiſe a generall admoninion in this manner.</p>
            <p>Beſides the calamities and manifold puniſhments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord hath chaſtiſed theſe Countries for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold tranſgreſſions, that now it is greatly to bee feared, leſt they be depriued of the greateſt treaſure which they haue in this world; that is, the puritie of the word of God, and that the famine which the Prophet ſpeakes of doe fall vpon theſe Countries. That they all had deſerued this puniſhment tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their vnthankfulneſſe, ſecurity, &amp; contempt of the word of God, yet is to be hoped, that if turning to God with their whole hearts, they ſhall repeate and implore the goodneſſe of God, and doe preſent their ſupplications to him againſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4814:14"/>
the diſmiſſion of the ſincere Preachers of the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the change of religion, which wil in time proue hurtful to them and their poſteritie: it may come to paſſe, that God for the merit and interceſſion of his ſonne, and for the glory of his moſt holy name, may repent him of his purpoſe, and may leaue his bleſſing amongſt them, that they may yet longer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the great Supper of his, to which they haue been inuited. Therfore to this end that God is to be inuocated with ardent prayers, and true groues, in this manner. <hi>O etérnall God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when this vnexpected change of Prince <hi>Wolfangus Guilielmus,</hi> bred diuers thoughts in the minds not only of the Courtiers and Councellors, but alſo of the commons of thoſe countries, who profeſſed the Auguſtane and reformed religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Prince to pacifie them and to hold them within the compaſſe of their obedience, publiſhed an Edict, wherein he declared, that he had no intention to make any diſturbance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his ſubiects in the point of religion: that he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare by relation, but obſerued it himſelfe: that many of his Officers, Councellors and other Miniſters, as alſo of his ſubiects dwelling in cities &amp; villages, are much troubled and perplexed in regard of his Chriſtian conuerſion, and publike confeſſion, and this his tranſition to the ancient Roman Church, as if by reaſon of the euident and knowne difference of religions, he meant not to maintaine them in the exerciſe of the religion, but in the point of religion would make innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and force them to embrace the confeſſion of a contrary religion. Therefore that no occaſion may be taken of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and of change of allegeance and dutie due vnto him, eſpecially in theſe touchy and dangerous times. And for as much hee neuer intended any ſuch thing, that hee thought good by theſe letters to teſtifie, that he hath reſolued not only to depart from the couenants and mutual obligations paſſed, but alſo with all his power to withſtand them, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the ſame, and to direct all his actions to the glory of God, the ſafetie of his countrie, and to the preſeruation of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which is equally to bee adminiſtred to all, without any reſpect of religion. And that he hopeth well, that all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Councellors, Officers, Commanders and ſubiects, wil
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4814:15"/>
conſtantly continue in their due obedience. For they who ſhall doe the contrary, and fall away from their dutie and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagance, ſhall no longer enioy their commodities and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which either they receiued of their anceſtors, or haue obtained by couenant and mutuall obligation. Theſe letters being publiſhed the 14. of Iune, when it was giuen out that the Prince of Brandenburge went about to bring in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med religion, he alſo by his Proclamation profeſſed, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhall enioy his religion, and that none vnder his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ſhall ſuffer any trouble for his conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>Now for the extinguiſhing of the vnkindneſſe growne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Princes of Brandenburge and Newburg, and to compoſe all controuerſie in a friendly manner, there was a meeting appointed the 10. of Iune, at Weſel, whether the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of Collen and the vnited Eſtates ſent their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors. Who when they perſwaded the Newburgians, that they ſhould within three daies diſmiſſe their ſouldiers at Duſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorpe, both the gariſon ſouldiers and the muſtered alſo, and that they ſhould forbeare to fortifie the towne. The New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgians wondring at this their Order, anſwered, that if Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick were reſtored into her former eſtate, that they would bee readie to doe what lay in them: but rather then they would yeeld conſent to the diuiſion of the countrie, they would firſt trie all manner of extremitie. Therefore when neither part would yeeld from their right, that meeting was fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>The Newburgians returning home, when the Prince vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the demands of the vnited Eſtates, to ſhew himſelfe inclinable for his part, conceiued in writing certaine Articles, by which hee ſuppoſed a compoſition might be made, and cauſed it to be preſented to the Eſtates: That the whole trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at Weſel conſiſted in this, that the Vnited Eſtates did hold, that the army muſtered by the Duke of Newburge ſhould be diſmiſſed: on the contrary, in the behalfe of the Prince, it was declared not onely for what reaſons that army was leuied, but alſo how neceſſarie it was, that the army ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from Gulick, and that towne to be reduced to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eſtate. Therefore when as the Eſtates themſelues haue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4814:15"/>
by their letters declared, that they gaue warrant to their Commiſſioners, to compoſe by way of prouiſion at the leaſt al controuerſies betweene the Princes, and to prouide, that as well their ſubiects as neighbours, ſhould be preſerued from al danger and trouble. Notwithſtanding that ielouſies and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt haue not a little growne by this, that againſt his priuitie and conſent, and otherwiſe then he had deſerued of them, he was diſpoſſeſſed of the Caſtle of Gulicke, and his garriſon ſouldiers put out of it, which poſſeſſion and detention hath been hitherto continued, vnder a pretence of a common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to both the Princes: whereby it is no hard matter to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, what ſuſpitions are like to ariſe thereby in the Empire, eſpecially with the Emperour himſelfe, who is chiefe Lord of the Fee, and other Electors and Princes, pretending any title to thoſe countries, that he ſhould be ſo diſturbed, in a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on purchaſed with ſuch danger, charge and trauell, and the ſequeſtration before time ſo much miſliked by the Eſtates of the low Countries, and with many reaſons oppugned againſt the Arch-duke <hi>Leopalde,</hi> ſhould there ſo eaſily be allowed. Seeing therefore there is danger, leſt thoſe that loue not the Prince ſhould draw this innouation into ſuſpition, and make that conſtruction, that it ſhould be thought, that more reſpect was giuen to the Eſtates of the Vnited Prouinces, then to the Emperour himſelfe, (whom the Prince doth acknowledge the chiefe Magiſtrate, and Lord of the Fee) but alſo would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Emperour, and prouoke him to enter into a new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe againſt the poſſeding Princes, and ſo would draw into danger a poſſeſſion hitherto, procured with great trauell and charge, to the great preiudice of the Prince, the which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Prince is loth to conceiue of the Eſtates v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, ſince by many letters they haue abundantly declared their good affection toward him, therefore that the Prince doubteth not, but that the Commiſſioners deputed by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors and Eſtates vnited, to compound this buſineſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering theſe reaſons, wil do their beſt endeuour, that reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion maybe made of the caſtle of Gulick, and of all the appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances thereto. For firſt of all, that the Prince of Newburg will not refuſe, (if the Prince of Brandenburge will doe the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4814:16"/>
ſame) at the firſt before any reſtitution made, to bind himſelfe by his hand and ſeale, and to promiſe in the word of a Prince, that he will attempt nothing againſt the Prince of Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg either now or hereafter, but in all points will keepe the conditions agreed vpon, and will be a faithful and equall kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the caſtle of Gulicke, as alſo of the caſtles, townes, skonces, and cities of theſe countries, without any mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, for the behoofe and vſe of him who ſhall be the lawful ſucceſſor and poſſeſſor, that hee will deliuer them to no third perſon, whoſoeuer hee bee, that hee will not vſurpe no more power ouer them, then the Prince of Brandenburge, but will gouerne and moderate all matters as before in an indifferent courſe of friendſhip, euen vntil the controuerſie be finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided. But to take away the difficultie which may happen, about the placing of an indifferent Gouernour in the caſtle, that the Prince of Newburge ſhall be well contented, that by the full conſent of the Princes, or of the Eſtates of the country, a certaine number of the Noble men of the countrie, fit for ſuch a buſineſſe ſhould be deputed, and from that time after, that the Gouernours, Commanders, Lieutenants, and other officers, bee choſen by lot, ſuch as may yeeld to each Prince their due obedience, and may afterwards ſubmit themſelues to him, to whom the ſucceſſion ſhal be adiudged: in the meane time that they do their ſeruice to both the Princes, and to the whole countrie, and be maintained by them: taking diligent heed, that no forrein ſouldiers come in amongſt them, or that their forces be increaſed without the priuitie of the Princes, a a law certaine alſo to be made, which ſhould be obſerued in admitting either of the poſſeding Electors and Princes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoeuer either of the foreſaid Princes ſhall recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally promiſe one to the other, that the Deputies of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Electors, and of the Vnited Prouinces, ſhould not onely ſubſcribe and confirme with their ſeales, but ſhould promiſe to procure, that the ſame ſhall be allowed and receiued of the ſubiects of their Principality, the letters of ratification and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, being ſent to each partie mutually, within the next moneth after the tranſaction and agreement concluded. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, that the Emperours conſent alſo, as the Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4814:16"/>
is to be entreated, and the Kings of France and Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanny to be requeſted, not onely by the Archbiſhop of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and the eſtates of the vnited Prouinces, but alſo of both the Princes, beſides the neighbour Electors and Princes, that they would hold this tranſaction firme and ſtable, and would defend each part, and maintaine againſt all vniuſt force. That the Counſellors of each part bee admoniſhed, that they reſt vpon this tranſaction, and attempt nothing againſt it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a Parliament to bee ſummoned, and that both the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould earneſtly endeuour that the Eſtates of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey be bound, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruing of this tranſactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and to impugne and withſtand by all means that partie that ſhall violate the ſame. When as therefore by this meanes not only the vnited Eſtates, but alſo all others may be aſſured that the Caſtle of Gulicke, (in the recouery whereof as they, ſo alſo the Kings of France and Brittany, the vnited Electors and Princes, yea euen the poſſeding Princes themſelues haue been at great charge,) ſhall neuer come into the poſſeſſion of any third perſon, and the Prince of Newburge openly teſtifie, that during this treaty his meaning is to vſe the ſouldiers ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Duſſeldorpe onely for the ſecurity of himſelfe and of the place, and ſo ſoone as the tranſaction is finiſhed will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe them, and enter into accord with the Prince of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburge, that in himſelfe hee may receiue ſome place for theſe moſt equall conditions, that he would beſeech and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh the deputies, that thus ſundry grieuances and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints taken away, there may be a reconciliation of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties procured, a courſe may with all ſpeed bee taken for the ſpeedy determination of the controuerſie, and that in the meane time all things may bee adminiſtred with an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent hand, according to the tenour of the former couenants. But if the Commiſſioners either all or ſome of them, haue not warrant to condeſcend to theſe moſt equal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, but ſhall thinke it neceſſary that this treaty ſhould bee adiourned for two or three weekes, vntill they may conſult with their principals (by whom they are ſent) and know their mindes, and that afterwards the ſame ſhall againe bee renued, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture alſo with the aſſiſtance of both the Kings, (who are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4814:17"/>
not to be left out in this buſineſſe) that the Prince will not be againſt it, ſo as they vndertake that no matter of hoſtility ſhall be attempted on either ſide. And that he doth hope that the Commiſſioners will vſe that care in the debating of the buſineſſe, that they may with the more facility arriue to their intended end, that is, to the reſtitution of their ancient confidence, and the conſeruation of peace and tranquillity.</p>
            <p>The King of Spaine when he vnderſtood what was done touching the Caſtle of Gulicke, moued the Archduke <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> to aſſiſt the Prince of Newburge, and to that end gaue order for the leuying of forces, and for money, which he ſent into the Low Countries. Therfore <hi>Albert</hi> calling backe the Captaines and other Officers, whom hee had before ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and declared the Marques <hi>Spinola,</hi> Generall of the army, to execute vpon the Cities of Aken and Mulheme the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of proſcription, which the Emperour had made againſt them, who leuied diuers Companies of horſe and foot, and prouiſions of al kinds for the warre, which was carried to the Maze. On the other ſide, the Eſtates of Holland laded three ſhips with artillerie, and drew to Schenke Skonce great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that is, 70. Companies of foot, and 18. troopes of horſe, beſides 1500. Waggons for carriage of their prouiſions.</p>
            <p>In the meane time the Prince of Newburge tooke diuers places in the Dition of Bercke, as Machem, Mandaue, Ellerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, and Burgh, which he alſo fortified with men and muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and bearing himſelfe as lawfull ſucceſſor, intending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to interre the body of the dead Prince, without the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity of the Prince of Brandenburge, who had withdrawne al his forces and ſtuffe from Duſſeldorpe to Cleue: but hee was deterred from that purpoſe by the perſwaſion of the Eſtates vnited.</p>
            <p>Some few yeeres a goe, there was ſet forth a booke at Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, with this title: <hi>Franciſcus Suares</hi> of Granada, of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Ieſu, Doctor of Diuinity, his defence of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and Apoſtolike faith, againſt the errours of the Engliſh ſect. This booke being examined in the Parliament of Paris, and found to containe in many places diuers propoſitions and doctrines, contrary to lawfull Kings appointed by God,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4814:17"/>
and to their regall power and authority, and againſt the peace and tranquillity of their kingdomes, it was vpon mature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation decreed and ſentenced, that thoſe doctrines and poſitions ſo ſcandalous, ſeditious, and inuented and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to the ſubuerſion of kingdomes and countries, and to arme their ſubiects againſt their Soueraigne Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yea and alſo detected to be manifeſtly ful of lies and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, euen in thoſe places where the examples of <hi>Clodo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Philip Pulcher</hi> are alleaged, are therefore worthie to be burnt by the common hangman in the outward Court of the Caſtle. This done, it was by proclamation forbidden, that no Printer ſhould print that Booke, or being printed ſhould bring it into the kingdom, reade it, write out, or keep it, much leſſe that any ſhould reade it in ſchooles, or giue vp the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions contained in it to be diſputed. And a Decree further was made, that the Decree of Theologicall faculty, made by vertue of a Parliament order, publiſhed in the yeere 1610. of renuing the cenſure of doctrines made, <hi>anno</hi> 1408. in the Councell of Conſtance, and alſo in the yeers 1578. and 1595. together with this late decree of Parliament, ſhould publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reade euery yeere the fourth of Iune, in the Colledges of the Theologicall faculty, and alſo of the Prieſts and ſtudents of Claremount Colledge, and of the begging Orders, and that at the ſute of the Kings Atturney General a diligent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſhould be made againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who had written any thing againſt this Prohibition. Furthermore it was decreed, that the Fathers of the ſociety of Ieſus, <hi>Ignatius Armundus,</hi> Rector of Paris, <hi>Cotton, Frontone,</hi> and <hi>Sirmund</hi> ſhould forthwith ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in Parliament, and there that they ſhould receiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and taxation, in that againſt their owne promiſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree made by their Generall, <hi>anno</hi> 1610. the foreſaid booke was printed, and was brought into the City of Paris, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate the authority of the King, to the diſhonouring of his perſon, and to the diſturbance of the peace of the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, adding this charge to them beſides, that they ſhould conferre with their Generall about the renuing of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and publiſhing the ſame with all ſpeed, and within the ſpace of ſix moneths next enſuing, ſhould publiſh and declare
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4814:18"/>
openly that thy haue obeyed and ſatisfied this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Parliament, and haue by their letters prouided, that no ſuch bookes hereafter ſhall bee written by any of this ſociety, and publiſhed abrode. Beſides the Ieſuites were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, that in their ſermons they ſhould diſſwade and deter the people from the liking of ſuch kind of propoſitions, and hereafter ſhould teach and preach the contrary, if they did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, they ſhould bee pronounced and declared by the Parliament guilty of high Treaſon. All theſe things were done and publiſhed the 27. of Iune, in the Pallace of the Parliament, in the preſence of <hi>Ignaſius Armundus, Carolus Tourus</hi> who appeared for <hi>Cotton, Frontonius</hi> Duke, and <hi>Iames Sirmundus,</hi> fathers, who were ſpecially required to be preſent at this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>In the former booke we ſpake of <hi>Sigefride Collonitius,</hi> how by an arreſt made on him he was ſtaied at Neoſtade, who not long after was by night carried to Vienna, and laid in the priſon, wherein wee mentioned that <hi>Guntherode</hi> had been kept before time. Comming to Vienna, by chance he ſpied a certaine Embaſſadour of Dreſda, whom he entreated to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him the fauour of the Elector of Saxony, who afterward did entreat in his behalfe to the Emperour in this manner. That <hi>Rodulph</hi> the late Emperour did many times vſe his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to excellent purpoſes againſt the Turkes, who therefore held him in great account, as indeed hee was for his vertue a wonder to all men, and a terrour to his enemies. Therefore that he beſought the Emperour, that in regard of his vertue and worth, and the fame of his name, hee would deale grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with him, and reſtore him to his liberty, eſpecially ſince now he hath made his innocency manifeſt to the world. By which act, he ſhall not only bind the loue of <hi>Collonitius</hi> and all worthy ſouldiers to himſelfe, but ſhall take away from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers all occaſion of ſiniſter conceit, that this which he ſuffers is for his religion and conſcience. In like manner the Count of Thuron entreated the Emperour in his behalfe, alleaging that it was not only permitted, but alſo commanded by God that one ſhould ſue for another; and therefore that hee truſting to the Emperours ſingular grace and clemency could
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4814:18"/>
not forbeare, but at the earneſt requeſt of <hi>Collonitius,</hi> to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his prayer and intreatie in his behalfe. For he had been in former times his fellow-ſouldier, in the warre againſt the Turkes, wherein he carried himſelfe faithfully and reſolutely, and by his famous exploits in that ſeruice, and valiant deeds hath purchaſed a name, that in thoſe parts will neuer bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Now if vpon any weakeneſſe or ouerſight hee hath committed any fault, he doth beſeech his Maieſtie, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the faithfull ſeruices, which he hath done to the houſe of Auſtria, he would pleaſe to pardon it, as proceeding not of mallice, and that out of his grace and goodneſſe, hee would diſcharge him of the arreſt, and ſuffer him to anſwer freely for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>To this time the Turkes with their incurſions and depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations into the countries adioyning, did the Chriſtians much miſchiefe. And hauing driuen a great multitude of cattell, were at laſt encountred in the way by the Heyduccians, in number about 800. who in a skirmiſh put the Turkes to flight, halfe a mile from Agria, and recouered the bootie out of their hands. The Baſhaw of Agria vnderſtanding this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feate, drawing foorth 1000. of his garriſon ſouldiers, renued the fight, but was ſo receiued by the ſaid Heyduccians, that he was beaten, hauing loſt 200. ſouldiers, and his horſe ſlaine vnder him, that he had much a doe to eſcape.</p>
            <p>The Heyduccians encouraged with this ſucceſſe, marched further, and on the ſudden aſſaulting a caſtle vpon Solnocke, tooke it, and carried away great ſtore of goods and cattell. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers skowring the countrie towards Buda, by chance light vpon a Lady going to be married from Strigonium to Buda, whom they chaſed, &amp; brought away a great deale of wealth, which they tooke from the company. Not long after hauing battered the caſtles of Balaſtera, Micoluta and Fellaco, they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrew 500. Turkes and more, and ſacked and ſpoiled all thoſe places about, and when the Turkes asked, why they ſo vniuſtly brake the Peace, they anſwered, that they gaue the occaſion, by the depopulations and excurſions which they <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>de, but they for their parts were good fellowes, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er cared for the Roman, nor the Turkiſh Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:4814:19"/>Some few yeeres paſſed, there aroſe certaine contentions betweene the Citizens and Senate of Frankford, about the publication of priuiledges, which had been decreed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them by the Emperour: for the appeaſing and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of which differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, were deputed Commiſſioners by the Emperour, <hi>Iohn Schuichardus,</hi> Elector of Mentz, and <hi>Lewes,</hi> the Lantgraue of Haſſia: who, after long and painefull exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the buſineſſe, brought the matter to that paſſe, that they accorded vpon certaine articles, of which we will onely mention the chiefeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Senate ſhould faithfully deliuer, and open all the priuiledges of the citie, 7. perſons being ſelected for the executing of the buſineſſe, an oath being firſt taken of them, in whole cuſtodie the Records are kept, that nothing ſhall be carried out of the Office, and next of the perſons ſelected, or deputed, for the reuiew of the priuiledges, that if they find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which may be preiudiciall to the citie, they ſhall conceale them: and other, if they ſhall ſeeme profitable for the citizens, that they ſhall faithfully reueale and diſcouer them to the Commons.</p>
            <p>Many other articles were agreed vpon, which rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned priuate commoditie, then the publick adminiſtration of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale. But the differences between the citizens and the Senat were compoſed, and that the Peace and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip might the better be preſerued betweene them hereafter, and that both obedience and reſpect might be yeelded to the Senate, and the Citizens without impeach enioy their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and priuiledges, there was decreed ſolemnly a publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe and obiteration of all thoſe things, which during theſe troubles haue been done or ſaid vrgently betweene them: that none of thoſe things ſhould be preiudiciall to any. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, that they ſhould forbeare all ſecret conuenticles and factions, and eſpecially that none, either Senator or Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen ſhould vndertake or attempt any thing againſt this tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action: the which ſince, the Emperor at the earneſt requeſt of the foreſaid Commiſſioners, the Senat and the Citizens hath ratified, and confirmed by his ſpeciall reſcript.</p>
            <p>The Companies of Smolenſco, who returned home <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4814:19"/>
of the warre of Moſco, did with great importunity chalenge their pay, and made great vprores in Polonia and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries thereabout, killing of the Countrie men, with no leſſe cruelty and furie then if they had been in the enemies Countrey, ſpoiling and burning all where they came. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Elector of Brandenburge, to remoue ſuch a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe from the borders of his Countrey, put his ſubiects into armes, and ſent to the Biſhop of Halles many waggons laden with prouiſions for warre. The Elector of Saxonie following his example, muſtered vp his ſouldiers alſo, and taking great quantities of armes out of his ſtorehouſes of Dreſda, and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temberge and his other armories, cauſed them to bee carried to diuers Caſtles and Townes.</p>
            <p>When the rumor was ſpread of the Gouernour of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, the Dukes of Mantua, Sauoy, and Lorraine, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that they had a mighty armie in readineſſe, the vnited Electors and Princes, were from diuers places admoniſhed, that they ſhould take circumſpect heed of a ſudden irruption; in the meane time the Moſcouites making a ſudden incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Lithuania, infeſted and annoyed all the Countrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with burning and ſpoyling. The Tartars in like manner waſting and making hauocke in the confines of Polonia.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Auguſt died the illuſtrious Prince, <hi>Philip Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicke</hi> the old Duke of Newburge, who by his laſt Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made the Duke of Wittemberge, and the Marqueſſe of Durlace his Executors.</p>
            <p>At this time the Prouinciall Diet was held at Lints, wherein all the hereditarie Prouinces of the Emperour, the Bohemians, Auſtriacks, Styrians, Carinthians, Carnio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanes, Sileſians, Luſatians, Morauians and Hungarians were aſſembled. It was propounded in that aſſembly, that of the Turkes part the peace was broken, by reaſon of many excur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and direptions of men and cattell, and other hoſtile at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of that kind, and that ſo much more certainely, that beſides Valachia and Moldauia, hee hath made challenge to Tranſyluania as his proper inheritance, and hath fortified it with Garriſon ſouldiers, vnder the gouernment of <hi>Gabriel Bethline,</hi> hath aſſembled the States of the Countrey, and hath
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4814:20"/>
denounced by his letters to the Emperour, that he ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to intermeddle in the Countrie. There was mention made of <hi>Gabriel Bethline,</hi> that he hath made him Gouernour, and the Turkes Vaſſall, that this Prouince might be vnited to the Turkes Empire; ſince then it brings more hurt then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to the Chriſtian world, it ſeemeth no part of wiſedome to abandon the Countrey to the Turkes, eſpecially conſidering the benefit which it bringeth to the Turke, and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe it bringeth to the Chriſtians, ſeeing it is ſo opportune for each party to make warre againſt the other. That it is no expecting the ratification of the peace, ſeeing the Sultan will by no meanes ſuffer that the Prouince ſhould ſweare to them both. Furthermore, it was in the Parliament demanded, ſince things hold no longer currant, but the Sultan laies claime to the Prouince, nor will ſuffer that hereafter the Germanes ſhould giue lawes to the Tranſyluanians, what ſhould be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to the Turke touching all theſe things: and ſince the Turkiſh Embaſſadour hath come without any commiſſion againſt the expreſſe conditions of peace, &amp; the Sultan hath no wil to ratifie the ſixth Article of the tranſaction, if his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour is to be admitted, and his letters to be receiued by the Emperour, to whom onely it is fit they ſhould bee deliuered. The laſt queſtion was this, whether a new tranſaction bee to bee made with the Sultan, ſince hee refuſed to ratifie the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and whether the Sultan ſtand to his promiſes or not (as hee hath done about Moldauia, Valachia, and Tranſyluania) if hee ſhould inuade Hungary before this Parliament bee finiſhed, what is to bee done, ſhould the Emperour deſcend to a meane of paſification, which by him hath not hitherto been violated?</p>
            <p>In the meane time came the Turkes Embaſſadour to Lints, by ſea. Therefore thoſe Delegates which were there preſent, in the behalfe of the hereditarie Prouinces and kingdomes, without delay deliuered to the Emperour their anſweres to al the propounded articles of the preſent conſultation: whoſe opinion was, that it behoued the Hungars to deuiſe a meane how this tranſaction made with the Sultan might be kept on foot, and yet without preiudice to the Emperours authority,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4814:20"/>
and in regard of the future and imminent neceſſity, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary meanes might bee prouided for the defence of the Countrie. The Tranſyluanians by all meanes labouring, and deprecating, that no army may ſet foot within their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince.</p>
            <p>During this Parliament the Mandate Declaratorie of the proſcription in the buſineſſe of Aken, was publiſhed in Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the 23. of Auguſt, by the Subdelegates of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to this effect. That after his happy acceſſe to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, hee vſed all ſpeciall diligence immediately, that in all places iuſtice might bee reſtored to her brightneſſe; and by this as by a meane the peace and concord of all eſtates and members of the Empire might be conſerued. Therefore after that hee vnderſtood in the very entrance to the Empire, of the troubles and confuſions which fell out from the yeere 1611. in his and the imperiall city of Aken, as well in ciuill as Eccleſiaſticall matters, that he tooke eſpeciall care and notice of this buſineſſe, and vnderſtood all which was at large ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by both the ſides, as wel in the behalfe of the old Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Senate, as of them who now are in place of authority, firſt at Vienna, and next at Ratisbone: moreouer that he might vnderſtand the whole truth, ſent from his Court to this City honorable Commiſſioners the next yeere 1613. that by this meanes hee might bee the ſurer not to ſwarue from iuſtice in the future deciſion of the buſineſſe: and how hee hath with mature deliberation examined, whatſoeuer hath been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to him in this caſe by the Electors, Princes, and the Eſtates Imperiall, of both Religions, and hath omitted no meanes which might in any ſort make for the true knowledge of this buſineſſe. And that it is euident by all the Acts and Records made in the courſe of iuſtice, that when in the yeere 1582. the firſt ſtirre began in this City, whereby the Senate was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued from his authority, and a great change made as well in Eccleſiaſticall as in ciuill matters, his brother <hi>Rodulphus Caeſar,</hi> out of his fatherly affection to this City, thought it to belong to his duty, maturely to prouide by what meanes this fire might be put out: for euen for this cauſe that he appointed the next neighbouring Princes to this City, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4814:21"/>
Eſtates of the Empire, as the Biſhop of Leige, the Duke of Iuliers and Cleue, <hi>Philip</hi> Buron of Vimeberge, and <hi>Philip</hi> Earle of Naſſaw, the Commiſſioners, who were very carefull and diligent to compoſe this buſines, but could not preuaile with theſe troubleſome ſpirits, who neglecting the whole authoritie of the Emperour, and the Commiſſioners, tooke vp armes in all fury, ſeazed themſelues on the publike armorie, and on the Senate; that the Emperour when hee vnderſtood this, yet proceeded not to extremitie of law, as yet, but euen vſed all gentleneſſe, and gaue a ſecond Commiſſion to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors <hi>Iohn</hi> of Triers, and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> of Saxony; but for all that, could preuaile no more then before, further then that their Subdelegates, who ſetting a part the danger of theſe troubles, aduentured themſelues into the citie, after much loſſe of time and paines, they left a plea of Receſſe there, which each part might vſe to the finall determination of the cauſe, in the Diet to be kept at Auguſta, <hi>anno</hi> 1582. That they did not onely accept of this Receſſe, but alſo deliuered their complaints to <hi>Rodulphus Caeſar,</hi> and ſpent many yeeres in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the buſineſſe before him, vntill at laſt <hi>anno</hi> 1593. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſummoned to heare the definitiue ſentence they appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for there in the preſence of the Emperour, and with his allowance, the ſentence was publiſhed againſt the defendants in this manner: That thoſe things which had been done in the citie, in a furious and vnlawfull maner, ſhould be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as void, and that all things ought to be reſtored into the ſame ſtate, wherein they were before the innouation. But whereas the other ſide which quailed in the iudgement, did not as yet ſatiſfie the excecutorie decree of the Emperour, it fell ſo out, that in the yeere 1598. that is, the fiftie after the condemnation, and publication of the definitiue ſentence, the ſentence of proſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was pronounced againſt them, for this inſolent and ſtubborne contumacie of theirs. By this courſe, being at the laſt brought to ſubmiſſion, and when vpon their othes they promiſed that they would in euery point obey the Emperors commandement, they were againe by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror receiued into fauor. But afterward in the 13. yere after, when not only againſt the executory ſentence publiſhed, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4814:21"/>
the declaration of the proſcription made, but alſo againſt the ſworne ſubmiſſion of the condemned perſons, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding for the moſt part were not natiue citizens, but ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and forreiners comming from other places. That the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Rodulphus</hi> tooke that behauiour of theirs in very il part, as a thing exceeding contrary and preiudiciall to his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and dignitie, in regard of the ſentence paſſed, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudged already, and forthwith to iuſtifie and make good his authoritie publiſhed againſt this tumultuous &amp; ſedicious company, a very ſeuere penall decree, with this meaning, that they ſhould giue ouer theſe attempts, and at the laſt obey the ſentence pronounced <hi>ann.</hi> 1523. by which meane they ſhould diſcharge their owne promiſes. And although he bee gone to heauen, yet there is no doubt, but if he had liued longer, he would neuer haue endured this iniurie done to his imperiall authoritie and dignitie, eſpecially ſeeing he had in his life ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Erneſt</hi> Arch-biſhop of Collen, and <hi>Albert</hi> the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke his brother his Commiſſioners, for the pacifying that tumult, and executing his decree, with moſt abſolute power to execute the ſame. But for as much as he being dead, in the time of the vacancie, and during the tumult, a plea of Receſſe hath been made and publiſhed in the citie, the 19. of May, <hi>anno</hi> 1612. by the Delegates of the Illuſtrious Prince Palatine, <hi>Iohn</hi> Adminiſtrator of the Palatine Electorate, and Vicar of the Empire, which doth directly croſſe this former execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie decree, and the promiſes confirmed by oath, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not only to the miſchiefe and hinderance of them, who now had won the right, which they ſued for, but alſo to the empairing of the authoritie of his brother deceaſed, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſucceeding Emperours, that a buſineſſe already now iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and ſentenced, and ſubmiſſions confirmed by oath, ſhould without any iudicial courſe, be ſo eaſily blowne away, that he after diligent examination of all circumſtances, and delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vſed touching the whole buſineſſe, cannot otherwiſe iudge and pronounce, but that the ſentence of the Emperour publiſhed the 27, Auguſt <hi>anno</hi> 1593. and the ſubmiſſions and promiſes which enſued the ſame, ſhould abide in full force, and that the commandement of the Emperour, publiſhed laſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4814:22"/>
of Octob. <hi>an.</hi> 1611. ought in all points to bee ſatiſfied, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideration to be had of the foreſaid receſſe or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parlance. Therfore that he hath appointed the moſt Excellent <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Archbiſh. of Collen, and <hi>Albert</hi> the Archduke his brother his Commiſſioners, in no other manner then before was done by the Emperour <hi>Rodulph</hi> his brother deceaſed, and hath giuen them power, that either themſelues, or they by their ſubſtitutes, ſhould ſignifie this his Mandate Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, to all the inhabitants of the imperiall towne and royall ſeate Aken, and according to the full power, wherewith they are furniſhed, ſhould by all meanes compell the parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to due ſubmiſſion and obedience, vntill they doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore all things to the ſame ſtate, wherein they ſtood, before the 6. of Iuly, <hi>anno</hi> 1611. Therefore that hee doth earneſtlie charge and command, al and ſeueral the citizens, inhabitants, and ſubiects of the foreſaid citie, whoſoeuer haue vnder any pretence attempted any thing againſt matters iudged, execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, obedience, and the commandement of the Emperour, publiſhed, <hi>ann.</hi> 1611. that forthwith they forbeare all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouations and ſtirres, vnder what colour or title ſoeuer, that they reſtore all things into the ſame place wherein they were, after the ſubmiſſion made <hi>anno</hi> 1598. vntill the 5. of Iuly, <hi>anno</hi> 1611. that they do in deed and truth, teſtifie their ſubmiſſion before the Commiſſioners or their Subſtitutes: that they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and doe all things which the Commiſſioners in his name command them, and attempt nothing againſt them, ſo as they will auoid his certaine diſpleaſure, and the puniſhments, included in the former executions, and in the laſt Mandate of the Emperour, the taxation of the charges, and the ſpeciall puniſhment and cenſure againſt them who haue profeſſed themſelues the ring-leaders and authors of thoſe troubles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſerued to his peculier order; as alſo on the other ſide, he promiſeth that he will adminiſter iuſtice to all, hearing all complaints, which any ſhall make againſt the old and lawfull magiſtrate, after the ſubmiſſion made. This Mandate Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, dated the 20. of Feb. at Budouitium, when it came to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> the Archd. hands, the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof was by him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Marques <hi>Spinola,</hi> who incontinently muſtring
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4814:22"/>
vp 30000. horſe and foote about the Thine, departed to Maeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriht, with 400. waggons, and 80. peeces of great ordinance, and from thence marched to Aken, bearing on his Tent the Eagle, the enſigne of the Empire. When he was come before the towne 21. Auguſt, and with great ſpeed had pitched his campe, and placed his ordinance, the next day he ſent his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers into the citie, to acquaint the Senate and Towneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with his commiſſion, and the Emperours commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who preſently aſſembling the Companies, entred into deliberation, how to giue ſpeedy remedy to theſe miſchiefes, that the citie might be ſpared. Therefore after diuers conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, the concluſion was, that the Clergy with the Popes Nuncio, with other principal Burgers, ſhould goe to <hi>Spinola,</hi> and humbly intreate of him fauor in the behalfe of the towne and the inhabitants. Which when they had done, after a very little conference, the city was yeelded to the Emperours plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. The towne being giuen vp, the ſouldiers of the Prince of Brandenburge were diſmiſſed out of the towne, with their armes and colours diſplaid, the 24. of Auguſt, and twelue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of horſe and foote brought into the towne: vpon whoſe entrie, the gates were ſhut, that none might paſſe any way. After this, the new Senate of the Proteſtants being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, the other Popiſh Senate, which had been diſcharged, was reſtored to his former place, and from that 28. day, was had the firſt meeting in the Senate to begin publike conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and certaine ſouldiers, by whoſe helpe, one of the Conſuls had eſcaped ouer the walles out of the towne, and ſome others, who were reckoned the chiefe authors of theſe troubles, were committed to priſon.</p>
            <p>The 15. of September laſt, were two great Armadaes in a readines, the one of the Turkes, to the number of 65. Gallies, which lay at Nauarine in Morea, which was the old Pelopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſus in Greece: another of the Chriſtians, who haue 85. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies well appointed at Meſſina in Sicilie, who had then taken two of the Turkes Gallies ſpies. It is ſuſpected the Turke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends this preparation for Calabria, the countrie is likewiſe prepared to bid him welcome.</p>
            <p>The matter thus ordered at Aken, <hi>Spinola</hi> with his armie
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4814:23"/>
marched toward Duren, whom the towneſ-men met in the way, and deliuered him the keyes, as to the Emperours Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant. In this time the Prince of Newburge leuied his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which conſiſted of 800. horſe, and 5000. foote, and the Count of Ridberge was employed to leuie more ſouldiers. On the other ſide the Prince of Brandenburge gaue order to his Captaines and Officers to leuie three Companies of foot, and 1000. horſe. Alſo the Palatine Elector vſed great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in leuying of forces, which hee drew to Bilifield to the appointed place vpon the marches of his Countrey, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his ſubiects that they ſhould be ready if occaſion of ſeruice ſhould require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spinola</hi> after that he had left ſouldiers in Duren, marched to Mulheme, which he tooke, and leauing 500. men to throw downe and to raze the trenches and bulwarkes of that place, departed and tooke in Berchem, Caſtre, Greuenbruke, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall townes, and put ſouldiers to keep them. Afterward going to Rhinbirke, he made a bridge of boates ouer the Rhine, that he might paſſe his armie for Weſell, Reſe, and Emmericke. This vnexpected iourney of <hi>Spinola,</hi> and ſucceſſe eſpecially at a time when there was now begun a friendly treaty, the Embaſſadors of the Kings of Britanie and France being preſent, and interceding for peace, gaue occaſion to the Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces to ſuſpect ill dealing: which cauſed them with all celerity and ſpeed to gather their forces and to haſten into the field.</p>
            <p>The Emperours Mandate being publiſhed at Franckfort, as we haue related before, that none ſhould be ſo hardy as to hinder the ancient Senate, but that they may enioy their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place, when the time of ſubmiſſion was now at hand, the Subſtitutes of the Elector of Mentz, and Prince of Darme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadte, came into the City the 11. and 12. of Auguſt, and ſhewing their letters of warrant, carefully aduiſed the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to obedience. The Citizens a little before this time had ſent certaine meſſengers to Lints, who exhibiting complaints againſt the old Senate to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſhould entreat that this abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of their authority might be ratified by the Emperour. But becauſe they were not as yet returned, a writing was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4814:23"/>
to the Subſtitutes, and a requeſt made by the Citizens that the execution of this Mandate might be reſpited but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the returne of thoſe Citizens, adding this proteſtation, that if it ſo fell out that the Emperour continued in the ſame mind ſtill, that they would not be againſt it, but in all points would obey his pleaſure. In the meane time ſome of the old Senators had taken their place againe, and now the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the Mandate for ſubmiſſion was at hand. Therfore they ſent for the ſeruants of ſundry tradeſmen, the 22. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, opened vnto them the meaning of the Mandate, and to auoide the danger and miſchiefe that might be fall them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, aduiſed them by all meanes, that they would not ſticke to their maſters and Lords, but depart ſome whither out of the City for a time. Then there went a rumor abroad, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they who were noted to be diſobedient, ſhould ſhortly ſee their names faſtened to the gallowes. This report whether it proceeded from the Subſtitutes, which they haue conſtantly denied, but the other affirmed, or whether it was deuiſed by ſome other, which is more probable, certainely it was the cauſe of a great vprore in the City. For the common people tranſported with rage and fury, did in flockes runne vp and downe the towne, and began to encourage and prouoke one another to commit ſome notable outrage, vntill toward euening, the whole force of their madneſſe being conuerted into the Iewes ſtreet, they ſpoiled and ranſacked the ſame. The Iewes at the firſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them, and with barrecadoes of all manner of ſtuffe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended their houſes, being aſſiſted by ſome of the Citizens themſelues. But the numbers of the raging multitude encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more and more, and the raſcals and looſe people flocking out of all quarters and corners of the towne, and mixing themſelues with the ſeruants and prentiſes gathered ſuch a head, that they were paſt reſiſtance, the Conſuls themſelues and other good Citizens being vnable to preuaile againſt their furie, either by force or by perſwaſion, for the rage the more encreaſed, the more it fell out that any were wounded in the tumult. For one was wounded in the arme, another in the eare, another in the eye: ſome being wounded to death fell to the ground. The next day the Citizens armed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4814:24"/>
and came vp with a competent number of horſe and foote into the ſtreet, and taking the goods from thoſe looſe fellowes, whom they could light on in the ſtreets, cauſed them to be laid vp for the owners. So there was an end made of this robbing and mutiny. The Iewes moued with the feare of this vprore, to the number of 1500. forſooke the City, reſoluing to dwell ſomewhere elſe.</p>
            <p>Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> in the meane time comming to Rhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berke, reſolued to beſiege Weſell, accompanied with 12000. horſe and foote. The Veſalians vnderſtanding this determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Spinola,</hi> preſently diſpatched meſſengers to Rhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berke, to gratulate his comming, and to preſent him with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cartlodes of wine, and to deſire of him the cauſe of his comming, that they might giue him ſatisfaction; who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them, that they muſt reſtore the City into the ſame condition and ſtate of gouernment wherein it ſtood in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and receiue his Garriſon into the towne. When this anſwere was deliuered to the Citizens aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in the Pariſh Church, they bound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by mutual othes, that they would fight to the laſt gaſpe for their Countrey, and die and liue together in the quarrell. But <hi>Spinola</hi> the 23. of Auguſt approching with all his Camp nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the towne, ſent certaine Companies aforehand to make an aſſault vpon the walles: which the towneſ-men iſſuing out of the towne receiued in ſuch manner, that they ſlew very many of them, eſpecially with the great Ordinance, which played from the towne: but <hi>Spinola</hi> marching neere with the the reſt of the armie, they retired into the towne: But he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed 18. Murall engins to be ſet againſt one place of the wall, threw downe one of the gates of the towne, which with the fall oppreſſed diuers, and ſtroke ſuch a terrour into the minds of the Citizens, that the women in all places came with their children running to the walles, and with weeping and wringing of hands entreated <hi>Spinola</hi> to ſpare them. A treaty hereupon appointed, an agreement was made, that one thouſand ſouldiers ſhould bee receiued into the City, and ſhould be billeted by the Magiſtrate vpon diuers houſes, who notwithſtanding liuing vnder military Diſcipline, ſhould bee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4814:24"/>
no burthen to the towneſ-men, nor receiue either meate or money of them. 2. That Gulicke being once reſtored to the former eſtate, by the Eſtates of the Vnited Prouinces, the City ſhould be againe diſcharged of theſe Companies of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. 3. That no change ſhould be made either in ciuil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or Eccleſiaſticall, and thoſe which concerne religion. 4. That the City ſhould retaine all her priuiledges without impeachment. 5. That by this occaſion no preiudice ſhould be offered to the Prince of Brandenburge. 6. That his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Miniſters with all their armes and prouiſions might remaine in the City ſo long as pleaſe them. 7. That the City ſhould keepe ſtill their Ordinances and all Prouiſion for war in their poſſeſſion. 8. That the Garriſon ſouldiers of the City ſhould depart with al their armes. 9. That it ſhould bee free for any Citizen to depart out of the City, whenſoeuer hee would.</p>
            <p>Theſe conditions being ſubſcribed by <hi>Spinola,</hi> and after to be confirmed by the Prince of Newburge, the City was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered into <hi>Spinola</hi> his hands.</p>
            <p>While theſe matters paſſed in this manner, Graue <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> Count of Naſſau, drew out his forces to the number of eighteene thouſand horſe and foot, appointing his rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous at Schencke Sconce, and taking to him <hi>William Henry Fredericke,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Erneſt,</hi> Count <hi>Chaſtilion</hi> alſo, and Sir <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race Vere,</hi> and many other braue Commanders, marching with his whole armie by water and land, hee came before E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericke, and ſuddenly ſurpriſed the towne, and put a guard in it. Next he marched to Reſe. Now the towneſ-men a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had ſent their Conſul to <hi>Spinola,</hi> promiſing him that they would receiue a guard from him. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Excellency had pitched his Campe, and ſummoned the towne to yeeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they refuſed, &amp; diſcharged their Ordinance againſt the Spaniards, which <hi>Spinola</hi> ſent with their conſent, profeſſing that they would bee neutrall, and would receiue no guard from one ſide or other. The Spaniards being thus ſent away and deluded, his Excellency commanded that the Artillary, and all prouiſion ſhould bee made ready to batter the towne which he intended to do very ſtrongly: but the Burgers when
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4814:25"/>
they ſaw there was no remedy, yeelded the towne, and receiued a guard from his Excellency: who from thence marching further, tooke in Gocha, Calcar, Gunep, and other townes ſituate in thoſe quarters.</p>
            <p>In the meane time <hi>Spinola</hi> neglecting the conditions of the treaty made with them of Weſell, encreaſed his guard againſt his promiſe and faith giuen: for he brought in three thouſand ſouldiers to the great hurt of the City, and ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Burgers, as he had done before at Duisburge, that not one Preacher durſt dare to preach in publike, in ſo much as their Churches ſeemed to be deſolate. But further making a bridge of boates ouer the Rhine, betweene Weſell and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, part of his armie he ſent to take Sante, part he employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to raiſe a bulwarke vpon the Rhine anenſt Weſel, by that meanes to keepe both the paſſage of the Riuer, and the City it ſelfe in his power. There had been carried from the ſiege of Gulicke into the towne of Weſell, 22. peeces of great Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with exceeding ſtore of powder and ſhot. All which hee permitted to bee taken away, and to bee reſtored to the Prince of Brandenburge.</p>
            <p>But his Excellency marching on ſtill, drew ſo neere to <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola,</hi> that he ioyned Tents with <hi>Spinolaes</hi> Tents, in ſo much as the P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdues and Sentinels might not onely talke, but alſo eate and drinke together. And when hee deſired to ſee the letters of his commiſſion, that he might know in whoſe name he entred into this expedition, <hi>Spinola</hi> deſired his Excellency that hee would in like ſort ſatisfie him, who cauſed ſo many Trumpeters to ſound the trumpet, as he had noble perſonages in his Campe.</p>
            <p>But to the declaration of the Eſtates of the vnited Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they would deliuer the Caſtle of Gulicke by way of ſequeſtration to the two Embaſſadors of the Kings of Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and France, the Elector of Cullen anſwered: That he knew not the minds of both the Princes, whether they will aſſent to this motion or no: and that hee knew as little whether theſe Embaſſadours haue ſufficient warrant from the Kings their Maſters to doe the ſame: that as hee conceiued, it was a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe rather of priuate honour, then the good of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4814:25"/>
which was ſtood vpon. That it cannot be denied, but that hee loſeth nothing of his honour, who reſtores that which is not his owne; therefore it ſhould bee fit for the common good, that on both ſides reſtitution ſhould bee made of all places, and all queſtions which haue riſen from hence, ſhould bee clearely taken away. After hee exhorted his Excellency, that he would pleaſe to ſpare neither time nor paines to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe differences, but that hee would bee willing to ſtay armes, that the matter may be drawne to a treaty. That hee alſo hath dealt earneſtly with <hi>Spinola,</hi> that would ſtay here, but that he would not hearken to the motion, vnleſſe he were aſſured that the Eſtates, and the Marqueſſe of Brandenburge would alſo ſit ſtill, and attend the iſſue of a treaty. Therefore that the matter might with more conueniency be brought to a treaty, that hee would wiſh his Excellency and the Eſtates to be effectually dealt withall.</p>
            <p>We ſpake ſomewhat before of the preparations of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of Millaine, and other Princes of Italy to armes. Now about the beginning of September, the armies of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Millain, and of the Duke of Sauoy, which are repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to exceed the number of 40000. haue met in the field, and fought a very bloody battell. Albeit they of Berne and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, and others, ſuſpecting that ſome trechery lyeth hidden vnder this pretence of quarrell, are vpon their guard, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide circumſpectly againſt the worſt: being alſo aduiſed dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently by the Proteſtant Princes and Eſtates, that they ſuffer not themſelues to be abuſed by any falſe pretences. Therefore certaine Imperiall Cities, as Strawsburge, Norimberge Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Wormes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ratisbone, Bibracke, Memming, Vinſhem, Rotenburge, Veiſſenburge, Offenburge, Noerdling, Hail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brun, Eſſing, Reutling, Suinfurt, Colmar, Halle in Sueueland, and others, haue with great ſpeed ſent their Embaſſadors, for a meeting to be held the 6. of Septemb. in this cauſe of Vlme, by reaſon of theſe tumultuous buſineſſes, and rumours of warres, the illuſtrious Princes of W<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttemberge and Anhalte ioyning with them in this buſines.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
